I don't mean to be disrespectful except
for you
do I'm Angela Duckworth I'm Steven
Dubner and you're listening to no stupid
questions today on the show we all need
feedback to improve so why is it so hard
to hear criticism if you don't give him
critical feedback what he could have
done better he tells you what a terrible
person you are he just denigrates you
also which is the more meaningful act
celebrating a friend's accomplishment or
supporting them through a loss most
people already know to be supportive
when someone is having a bad day so it's
okay to ditch them because you already
know that whereas if something good
happens I want to be there for the
[Applause]
champagne Stephen Angela everyone I know
recognizes that feedback makes you
better whatever it is that you're trying
to do but nobody I know likes to be
criticized so you know what do you think
that is so I do love that question but
let me ask you a couple questions about
the question so you're linking feedback
and criticism negative feedback right
when you said feedback makes you better
I believe in that more than I believe in
just about anything on Earth if you want
to improve you need really good feedback
but I would also say there are a lot of
forms of feedback including negative
feedback that aren't really criticism
that aren't painful at all like what
well I think about like I'm a kind of
mid career golfer right one of my
favorite things about golf is that the
feedback loop is super tight it's so
short cuz it's immediate right immediate
you see if the ball went where you
wanted it to go and also once you start
to learn a little bit about the physics
of the swing and how it works you become
self- diagnosing so you not only know
where the ball went you know why it went
off course exactly and that to me is a
really exciting thing because like you
said it's hard to learn or improve at
anything without getting feedback but
the kind of feedback you're talking
about you're talking about criticism of
how I did a certain thing assessed by
someone Beyond me yeah I think it's
usually from another person right it's
not from just like looking at the ball
so I agree that everybody says they want
it and nobody really does and honestly I
think it is a universal Paradox that we
know it's good for us and we know that
it's painful I've asked a lot of
different people a form of this question
in fact I recently asked it to David
burn a songwriter performer Talking
Heads Talking Heads then I just asked
him you know Talking Heads were a very
very well-reviewed rock band they were
like a total critic's favorite it be
really hard to find a Critic from back
then that mattered that didn't like
Talking Heads but I asked him about
negative reviews and he sounded as
wounded and fragile as anybody which is
that yeah they really really really hurt
he could probably still remember some of
them he did remember them but here's the
way I feel about accepting criticism if
people are coming at you with feedback
that is useful for improving yourself
then you should run at it and embrace it
even if it's painful but if they're
criticizing you on a dimension
that is either dogmatic or personal or
unbalanced which you often encounter so
really what you have to do is you have
to learn to sort out the different
categories of criticism and they kind of
go into heaps and the Heap that has
critical stuff that's useful is really
small let's say I write an article or do
a podcast that gets 500 comments or
replies on Twitter it doesn't take that
long to triage through and say okay
those 400 are like saying yeah yeah it's
nice but then there's 80 that say oh I
can't believe you let this person come
on your show to say these things and to
them I say okay that's a listener who's
got a point of view that I disagree with
I think it's nice to have people you may
disagree with voice their views and hear
about them right and then there might be
10 or 15 that actually say you know you
tried to make this point but ultimately
you failed because you didn't bring in
this variable or this idea and to me
that is the most valuable yeah that tiny
little sliver so I feel the biggest
problem with criticism and accepting
feedback is that since the vast majority
is mostly noise most people don't want
to sift through to get the signal that
will actually make them better yeah I
think that's right and I think even when
you do know that you're talking about
really useful feedback from a credible
Source I personally still find it hard
to take I really do would you rather
they say I love this and everything you
do
okay I'm of two minds part of me really
does just want un adulterated praise you
know at the end of my class my students
rate my class and then they have these
open-ended comments and I'm hoping to
get 10 out of 10 and you know when I see
a students giving me a three out of 10
which happens I'm awake at night
worrying about it are they Anonymous
completely Anonymous so you can't seek
out and punish that person I can't fail
that person but you would if you
could I hope not but okay so that's
Parton me right I just want but there's
another competing part of me that wants
to get better and wants to make the next
class better and I think this explains
why everybody knows that feedback makes
them better and then nobody wants it
it's not inconsistent when you just
realize that people contain multiple
selves multiple motives and I think even
just understanding that's been helpful
my friend and you know him as well Adam
Grant taught me this trick So Adam asks
for feedback all the time especially I'm
thinking of when he gives talks and if
you don't give him critical feedback
what he could have done better he tells
you what a terrible person you are he
just denigrates you that's basically how
it works no he's very persistent though
he keeps asking and he has this trick
which is that he doesn't like the
experience of getting negative feed but
then he grades himself on how he
received the feedback so it gives him an
opportunity to you know still get a 10
out of 10 because you could get a three
out of 10 from the student and then you
could say oh but you know what I give
myself a 10 out of 10 for listening to
the feedback so outside of let's say
teaching a class or writing a book do
you you seek out and or desire honest
assessments of things you do for a short
while I was asking for numeric ratings
on dinner like okay scale from 0 to 10
how are we rating this enchiladas seven
how could I make it an eight but did you
accept that yeah you know one thing I
will say is that when it comes to things
that are not part of your identity I
mean the Paradox is that the core
identity of a person is the actual thing
that they do want to probably get better
at right right so say somebody says like
you know what Stephen you're a little
condescending actually some students
have told me like I'm a little
condescending and I name drop and when I
first read that in my comments on my
course I was like what that's ridiculous
but I think it cut so close to the Bone
because in my identity I really don't
want to be that sort of person but
that's the exact kind of criticism I
should be open to so I think I've
achieved some kind of at least awarness
do you think that's progress I do think
that's progress I think it's also fair
to ask yourself well okay this person
has a critical thing to say I recognize
it as legitimate but there's also a
reason that you do it and you're okay
with that but if you do that then you're
never going to change right okay well
here's an important thing I think you
have to acknowledge that there's great
heterogeneity among humans and no one
likes everything so here's an example
when I was in grad school I did an MFA a
writing program and there were workshops
and seminars seminars were kind of
instruction workshops where students
would bring in their writing so you
would would get somebody's manuscript
and it would usually be like 30 to 50
pages of a novel or a short story take
them home and read them then you'd come
in and you'd discuss them as you can
imagine those conversations could become
very fraught with all different sorts of
emotions there were all kinds of clicks
friendships enemies there were people
who liked a certain style of writing and
others who didn't so but what was really
interesting to me is once you get a few
weeks into the semester it was totally
predictable who would like what and why
so you knew probably even before you
enter the room everybody knew really who
was going to like it in an Earnest way
who was going to like it in a grudging
way who was going to dislike on and on
and on and then I started to think well
what if you brought in here some
manuscript that didn't have a name on it
Anonymous and let's say I'm the
professor and I slip in a manuscript
that's not written by someone in the
class maybe it's Virginia wolf maybe
it's Tolstoy and can I tell you what
Virginia wolf would have gotten the crap
beat out of her in that class including
by people who think they love Virginia
wolf ah so you're saying that these are
biased reviews right I'm saying a
there's bias and B there's taste there's
preference and so when you are the
person getting the criticism you have to
say to yourself you know what if it's
golf the shot was good or Not Right But
if it's subjective you have to say there
is a group of people out there who are
not interested in this idea for reasons
that I may think are legitimate or not
and I'm going to be okay with having
that criticism exist okay but Stephen
what if three people three separate
people say that you're condescending and
name dropping yeah like if you got that
feedback okay so here's what I think you
don't want to do if you're a banker
you're a writer you're a parent creative
person whatever the biggest mistake we
can make and I've made this mistake is
let
criticism hurt you to the point where
you narrow and shrink your drive when I
was a young writer just moved to New
York I was writing all different kinds
of things and I had a play going that I
was so excited about and then I happened
one evening to have dinner with a much
older gentleman that I'd gotten to know
a guy that I'd done some work for and he
was a playright I was a word processor
for a living this was back when people
were just starting to get their things
revised on computer so I was like a guy
who knew how to do that so I had retyped
a couple of his plays and so we became
friends and we went out to dinner and he
said what are you working on and I told
him about this play and he was a really
nice guy he hated it hated it he said
wow it's not a good idea it's not going
to work I wouldn't spend any time on
that and it broke me I literally never
went back to it because I didn't have
the confidence now I'm not saying that
would have been a good play but I really
regret that because I let someone else's
criticism which may or may not have been
legitimate shrink my choice set I want
to be the only one shrinking my choice
set and that's where I feel that
criticism hurts a lot of people unduly
the guy can't even use a word processor
for God's sakes
what do you know but at the end of the
day he's one person and I'm the one
that's making it I need to forge on
until I'm convinced that it's no good or
good so I think the summary
recommendation is that we should be
hungry for feedback and actually that
appetite for knowing what other people
think doesn't mean that we have to
swallow everything you know I have read
about research by psychologists that
make feedback more effective by
including a preface do you know about
this research I think I remember being
one of the blind reviewers did you give
them some good criticism I actually
mostly praise I love this paper so
here's the preface these are the 19
words you're supposed to say before you
tell someone how much they've screwed up
I'm giving you these comments because I
have very high expectations and I know
that you can reach them I think it's
genius this is the work of David joerger
and Jeff Cohen and other psychologists
and it's called the wise feedback paper
it's actually now quite well known and
it was a random assignment study I
remember it very well actually from
reading it the first time where students
are writing essays in class and the
miraculous effect was that the students
who got this short encouragement just 19
words were much more eager to do
something with feedback so they revised
their essays I think in some subsequent
studies they did better academically
especially students who had been
struggling and it's terrific advice for
all of us feedback givers and we all are
in one way shape or form which is I
think what we're trying to communicate
to people is useful information and this
little preface inoculates the receiver
from the kind of like I'm not good and
you don't think I can make it and I
think a lot of times when people get
criticism they think the real message is
that they're not going to make it and
this little 19w preface says no the
reason I'm giving you this feedback is
because I think you are going to make it
and this is going to help you get there
I will say as a receiver of feedback not
a dispenser but as a receiver I kind of
am attracted to the idea of radical can
as some people call it obviously every
environment is different but some of the
criticism that I remember the most as
feeling hurtful it was unspoken
criticism kind of like a passive
aggressive you know I think it was Men
Out of Love honestly like my first life
was playing music in a band and we were
pretty noisy kind of borderline Punky
band and once in a while one of my
siblings or someone would say hey I see
you're playing so and so I'm gonna come
see you and I'd say you don't really
need to do that but then they would show
up I knew it wasn't the kind of music
that they would like and then I remember
one time we're playing here in New York
we didn't live here it was a big deal
and I had a sibling come after the show
I remember him saying you guys really
looked like you were having a lot of fun
up
there and I remember just thinking it's
okay to say wow this is not my kind of
thing but you know way to go whatever be
like me saying at the end of this
podcast Angela you really said a lot of
words
there so this idea of radical cander
which I think it's like a business
phrase right made famous by Ray doio of
Bridgewater Associates and Kim Scott
right Kim Scott wrote a book called
radical kander and I think the basic
idea is when you have a culture of Truth
telling like at all times I mean you
know Stephen your breath smells that
joke there was both unfunny and
inappropriate I'm out of here yeah slam
the door on the way out and I'm very
sympathetic that if it can really be
done well I think the problem is when
you have some people who are bought into
radical cander and other people who hate
it I think an exercise for you and me
after this session is over we should
each send each other an email with some
feedback can we make it only nasty
feedback we'll have to agree to press
the button at the same time so I can't
make mine nastier based on how nasty you
were to me is that a deal well okay I'm
fine with that but I just want to tell
you one thing I'm giving you those
comments because I have very high
expectations and I I know you can reach
them still to come on no stupid
questions Angela teaches Steven how to
support a friend in need look use your
judgment I need the script I don't want
[Music]
judgment okay Angela Duckworth question
for you okay it could be real but it's
mostly a thought experiment so let's say
you've got a choice a binary choice you
can send one note of congratulations
to someone who you feel deserves it or
you can send one condolence note to
someone who really needs it which do you
send and why and actually I can make it
more realistic so I happen to know that
you know Pete Carol football coach of
the Seattle Seahawks yes of course yeah
you know him through your grit work and
so on I do and he's also an adviser to
my nonprofit character lab and I know
that you're not a big football fan not
especially but you've heard of football
you know what it is it's mostly from
Pete Carol okay so here's a guy who's
been a a very successful coach for many
many years and apparently is a nice and
charismatic human is that true yes he's
a very nice and charismatic human like
genuinely so let's imagine that the
Seattle Seahawks are playing in the
Super Bowl which they have done in the
past they have and they've won one
they've lost one I think that's right
they've won one and lost one they won
one for sure okay so let's say that Pete
Caroll and his Seattle Seahawks are
playing in the Super Bowl and they win
in one version of this thought
experiment and the other version they
lose to which event do you respond more
quickly with a note the congratulatory
note or the condolence note and why I
would in that hypothetical be much
quicker to congratulate than to extend
condolences because why you know I think
because surely he's already gotten
15,000 other congratulatory notes
everybody wants to be his friend right
now I'm just going to be lost in a sea
of congratulations yeah so is the
congratulations for him for you well I
think that there's one reason why the
congratulations come faster and I always
hesitate with the condolence note
because I always actually find it hard
to do it well I often find myself
writing things like let me know if
there's anything I can do and it's
blindingly obvious that there's
literally nothing you could do now when
you write a note of congratulations I
think for me it's very intuitive and I I
happen to know there's also scientific
research behind this is that the job of
somebody writing a note of
congratulations is to match the level of
energy and the tone of the person who's
experiencing the victory when you say
it's their job with the outcome being
what I think when somebody has something
good happened to them what they're
looking for is to have it kind of like
first of all sustained right and second
of all like it would be great if you can
be in some kind of positive Echo chamber
and like your good fortune gets
magnified and like you understand what
big deal this was okay imagine this
imagine that you're applying for some
kind of job or fellowship and you get it
so Stephen there are actually four
different ways you can respond when
somebody has good news all right there's
active and there's passive and then
there's constructive and destructive so
the research from Shelley Gable says
that what people are looking for is
active constructive responses to Good
News you know you match my tone you're
enthusiastic you ask for elaboration you
want to know more all right that's the
best the worst is probably active
destructive where you're high energy but
you're like this is terrible like
imagine the taxes on that Fellowship
right and and that's really really toxic
but there's two other not so great ways
to respond to a friend and one is
passive constructive so you know you're
being constructive but like you're not
matching me in my energy you're kind of
like oh I guess that's nice and then
finally there's passive destructive
where you're like you know have you seen
the butter exactly exactly it's like
Stephen oh my gosh this Fellowship
actually happened I can't believe it and
you're like so I wonder what time dinner
is going to be and number four is the
best you're saying to be clear passive
destructive is the best that's exactly
what I want you to take home no Stephen
please be actively constructive I know
you can do it okay so if scientists have
thought through so much the optimizing
congratulations why not condolences why
don't you know as much about that cuz
you were saying that you don't really
know how to do that well why not well I
think if it's in writing especially
right when you're sending somebody a
note you feel like you're just saying
cliche things that feel insincere you
end up saying things like I'm sorry for
your loss if there's anything I can do
please let me know my thoughts are with
you and honestly those things are
usually completely true but I think
sometimes it just feels unthoughtful or
not not specific enough what does the
science tell us about being on the
receiving end though when you're
grieving mourning experiencing a loss
and again a loss could range from a
loved one dying to not getting a
promotion to losing a football game Etc
well I'm most acquainted with the
research on how to be a good friend to
someone who's grieving or experiencing
distress in person okay so tell us what
you know about that so the technique to
use is something called supportive
listening and in a nutshell it is that
when you are listening to someone who's
going through a real emotional episode
you want to be empathic and you know you
don't want to LEAP to what many people
do which is to try to like get them out
of their Funk right away try to problem
solve for them mostly what people need
to feel is to feel heard and seen so you
kind of echo back what they said if
someone says like oh my God I just feel
so lonely don't say oh you know there's
always reasons not to feel lonely say
what I hear you saying is that you feel
lonely and and that must be really hard
okay I'm sorry that sounded like a
Saturday Night Live version of geving
what I hear you saying is you feel
lonely well yeah I know it sounds like
it shouldn't work right I don't mean to
be disrespectful except for you do well
maybe a little bit but no so you're
saying it's literally say what I hear
you saying is the thing that you just
said yes it's like you're reflecting
back to that person now look I know
you're skeptical right what I hear you
saying is that you think I'm skeptical
about this what I hear you saying
Stephen exactly okay and is that because
mirroring is a form of flattery or
identification you know I think
mirroring is just a signal that the
person has actually received the message
I mean if I'm having an argument with my
husband or even if I come home with a
problem and he immediately thinks like
oh well here's how you solve your
problem I feel like he skipped an
important stage in the conversation and
that stage is that I need to feel heard
and I need to feel like there was a
sympathetic response before we get into
plans that I might make to solve my
problem and I know it sounds like it
shouldn't work but you should go try it
okay so this is super interesting and
useful I do want to try it so okay I'm
I'm thinking this let's say I come home
one day and my wife says uh it's been in
such a hard day I've spent 4 hours on
the phone no joke with the health
insurance company just trying to get
them to do the thing that they've
already supposed to have been doing and
that we're paying them a fortune for
every month and even though it was 4
hours we didn't get an outcome so you're
saying the first thing I should do is
say what I hear you saying is that you
just spend a lot of time that was really
frustrating and then what do I say and I
can tell my wife who's you know pretty
sharp she's going to say why are you
telling me what I just said and then
I'll say Well Angie told me to because
she says this works she said it would
sound sincere right because if you can
fake sincerity you've got it made so if
I say what I hear you saying is that you
spend all this time and then what comes
next well look use your judgment you
don't have to say like what I hear you
say I need the script I don't want
judgment I mean just take a beat right
just to be like oh God that sounds awful
4 hours wow you must be incredibly
frustrated and then it could be like oh
well maybe I could call this person or
whatever but if you just leap forward to
the stage of the conversation where
you're problem solving or giving advice
you're not matching the person's
emotional state and I think personally
speaking but also based on the research
people need to feel like there's some
acknowledgement okay but let me go back
to the original so Pete Carroll the
coach of the Seahawks you said you
didn't like the idea of sending the note
that person it would be different so
let's say condition a Seahawks win the
Super Bowl and you have the opportunity
to the next day show up and congratulate
Pete Carol in person thought experiment
B they lose you have the opportunity to
show up and offer condolences in person
which you more likely to do
then uh I would rather be the one to
offer congratulations because it's
better for you or because it's better
for him I guess I was just being selfish
there because the whole scenario is just
a better one I mean look as a friend I
think it is is maybe equally important
that you help people enjoy their good
days and also get through their bad days
it's just I think that most people
already know that the job of a good
friend is to be supportive when someone
is having a bad day so it's okay to
ditch them because you already know that
whereas if something good happens I want
to be there for the champagne no let's
just imagine the following let me give
you a different thought experiment okay
you come crying to me right what's the
likelihood that me or one of your
friends is going to know what to do it's
reflexive the likelihood is high that
people will have some intuition to do
the right thing which is to listen let's
go for a walk let's grab a drink or what
I'm hearing is that you had a bad day
right or that sounds really hard some of
us need that reminder but I'll just say
that for many of us when our friends
have something really good happened to
them it can be less intuitive for some
people to realize you have a job there
too and that is to help your friend
Revel in their good fortune and I think
there may be a lot of people who maybe
to their own surprise if they ask their
friends would find that you know they
could be a little more positive when
their friends come to them with good
news I would just offer or ask about one
counterbalance which is that I have a a
friend a close friend who has several
kids but the first kid died at a very
young age and it was really tragic but
he once commented to me he said you know
especially when it first happened nobody
would ever bring it up to me he said
they seemed sure that they shouldn't
bring it up because I wouldn't want to
talk about it the fact is that's the
only thing I wanted to talk about but
none of them wanted to talk about it and
I was really moved by that and thought
you know that might be an extreme
example but I have a feeling that happen
a lot more than we think how about this
as an answer to your question about you
know what could his friends have done
this couple's friends have done
differently and also an answer to your
question about do you write the
condolence note do you write a note of
congratulations I think the lesson from
social psychology is that we are very
often wrong when we try to mind read
when we try to guess what other people
want us to do we often make assumptions
that are just wrong and the antidote
especially in a longer term relationship
because it's not like the last time
you're going to see your friend is to
say like what do you want me to do here
I mean just ask like I'm not sure you
want to talk about this or whether you'd
really prefer we not talk about this can
you tell me and then take the cue from
them because you know mind reading feels
accurate but is most often not as
accurate as you think what I hear you
saying Angela is that I should just ask
people what they would like me to do is
that accurate that's an accurate
statement I'm so glad you asked I
learned learn something today thank you
you're
welcome no stupid questions is part of
the Freakonomics radio network this
episode was produced by me Rebecca Lee
Douglas and now here's a fact check of
today's questions in the first half of
the episode Steph and Angela discuss the
concept of radical cander and Angela
jokes that Steph has bad breath and that
he is not funny clearly Angela was being
factious but it's important to note that
radical cander does not mean brutal
honesty Kim Scott the author of the book
radical cander refers to that type of
language as quote obnoxious aggression
and she says that when practicing
radical cander feedback should be
delivered in a kind and helpful manner
hopefully Stephen and Angela take this
into account before sending those
check-in emails they sounded ruthless
and I'm glad I wasn't a part of that
deal in the second half of the show
Steph was slightly wrong about the Super
Bowl history of the Seattle Seahawks
their record under Pete Carroll is one
in one but in total they've won one
Super Bowl and lost two if you're
curious about what drives this coach's
success take a listen to episode 6 is
incompetence a form of dishonesty
Stephen and Angela debate the value of
top level goals including Pete Carroll's
famous mission statement always compete
later on Angela confesses that she often
struggles with what to say when a friend
is grieving the death of a loved one
this is a common feeling that many
well-intentioned people experience and
so I thought I'd share a quick list from
Harvard Medical School of things to say
and do the next time a grieving friend
needs you don't say how are you since
the answer is often obvious Instead try
how are you feeling today also don't
just say you're there if they need
anything it may be uncomfortable for
them to reach out for help instead be
specific when offering help bring over
dinner or help them clean the house and
finally remember to keep reaching out
your friend may need you more after the
first few weeks when others may stop
calling no stupid questions is produced
by Freakonomics radio and Stitcher our
staff includes Allison krao Greg rippen
James Foster and Karen Wallace our theme
song is and she was by Talking Heads
special thanks to David burn who still
remembers those bad reviews and Warner
Chapel Music if you you'd like to listen
to our show ad free subscribe to
Stitcher premium you can also follow us
on Instagram and Twitter at nsq show and
on Facebook at nsq show also if you
heard Steven or Angela drop a reference
to something that you'd like to know
more about you can always check out
freakonomics.com
nsq where we link to all of the studies
and references that you heard here today
thanks for
[Music]
[Applause]
listening Steve
St Angela caught me napping stepen wake
up are we making a podcast I was
wondering what these microphones were
doing
here Stitcher